Finding Aid for Richardson Family Papers 1864-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richardson Family Papers 1864-1966
Richardson family.
2 oversize folders
2 linear feet
Owosso, Shiawassee County, Michigan, family. Correspondence and other materials relating to daily life and family activities; collection of sheet music; and photographs.
85372 Aa 2; UAx UAl
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Richardson family (donor no. 5739 ) and came to the library in 1975.
The collection is open for research.
Two families, the Cooks and the Richardsons, settled in Shiawassee County, Michigan in the 1860's. On January 1, 1890, Emma Cook, the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Seth Cook of Maple River married Charles S. Richardson, the son of Merritt and Mary Richardson who had come to Michigan from Massachusetts. Charles had two brothers, Frank and George.
Before her marriage in the period 1881 to 1889, Emma Cook taught schools in rural Shiawassee County. Letters to her received from friends and relatives discuss life and times of their situations. Lee Wheeler, her uncle, was a cooper in Nevada. Will S. Cook, her brother worked in an insane asylum in Pontiac, Michigan, while friends Ernest and Walter Gannon lived in California, then later attended Michigan Agricultural College in East Lansing, Michigan. Emma's sister Otie Cook was also a teacher, who later married a Mr. Jennings, an undertaker, late in life (the 1940's).
Vera Richardson was the eldest daughter of Emma and Charles Richardson. Their other children were Don, Abigail (Gail), and Max. Vera was born in 1891 or 1892, attended the Michigan Normal College in Ypsilanti, Michigan from 1911 to 1915 or 1916, and became a pianist and radio star well known in the state. She studied in New York under a Mr. Swayne from January- March 1915. She married Mr. Leigh S. Simpson who was from Owosso also, attended Michigan Normal College (graduated before Vera), and had become a high school manual arts teacher. He taught in Detroit and Mt. Clemens while Vera was still in school. He served in the army (teaching) in 1917-1918, in South Carolina and Georgia. Later he became a dentist and had his office on Woodward Avenue in Detroit. They lived in Detroit after their marriage.
Vera's brother Don attended Michigan Agricultural College in East Lansing about the same years she was in Ypsilanti. He went back to Owosso, married a girl named Ada, and was running the Richardson farm when his father died in 1933. Gail and Max were considerably younger siblings. Gail became a librarian and worked at the Detroit Public Library. She lived with or near Vera and Lee. Max eventually owned a welding business on Vanderkarr Road, Owosso. He spent parts of 1942 and 1943 with the army in Jackson, Mississippi and Texarkana, Texas. After the war he married Evelyn Jetoria White. Charles S. Richardson died in 1933 and Emma died in 1934.
The Richardson family papers (letters, photographs, and business records) illustrate the lives of ordinary rural Americans from the 1860's to the 1940's.
Subjects:
Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; Owosso (Mich.); Richardson family.; Women--Michigan--Owosso.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Dwellings.; Fabric shops.; Fishing--Michigan.; Hospitals--Michigan--Owosso.; Hunting--Michigan.; Interiors.; Richardson family.; Schools--Michigan--Owosso.; Washington School (Owosso, Mich.); Women.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biographical Material (obituaries) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Letters (Box 1)
  - Seth Cook Deeds 1811-1882 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning death of L.G. and Lenora Cudley December 30, 1938, June 29, 1962 (Box 1)
- Family letters
  The collection includes a small series of family letters, some deserving of particular mention. Will A. Richardson wrote letters home from Tennessee in 1864 and 1865 where he was with the Union Army (10th Michigan Vol. Cavalry). Although the relationship is not clear, Merritt and Mary are addressed as parents. Four other people's relationships to the Richardsons are unclear, too: Debbie Beers, Seth Beers, and Gertrude and Maude Layton. It seems that Merritt and Mary were the guardians of the latter two. The girls call them Uncle and Aunt. They refer to Seth as Brother. Debbie ran a boarding house for the Union Pacific Railroad Company in Buford Station, Wyoming and her letters to Aunt Mary Richardson are full of life and times in this "profession" among the railroaders. Gertrude was a single secretary and lived in South Omaha, Nebraska; she is the working girl of the 1880's and 1890's. Seth served in the Spanish American War.
  - Will A. Richards to his parents 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - Charles S. Richardson correspondence 1880-1916 (Box 1)
  - Frank Richardson correspondence 1886-1900 (Box 1)
  - George Richardson correspondence 1886-1899 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Seth Beers 1881-1895 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Maude Layton 1886-1893 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Gertrude Layton 1884-1890 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Mary Richardson 1877-1895 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Mary Richardson 1896-1903 (Box 1)
- Emma Cook
  Letters to Emma Cook are from family and friends in the period of the 1880s and 1890s. Also preserved within this series are Emma Cook's teaching certificates.
  - Letters to
    - Miscellaneous undated, 1880-1891 (Box 1)
    - From Flora 1886-1888 (Box 1)
    - From C.S. Richardson 1886-1898 (Box 1)
    - From Walter Gannon 1884-1886 (Box 1)
    - From Ernest Gannon 1886-1889 (Box 1)
    - From C.E. Skinner 1885-1891 (Box 1)
    - From Lee Wheeler 1882-1888 (Box 1)
    - From Alice Jackson McKnight 1819-1891 (Box 1)
    - From Maud 1883-1896 (Box 1)
    - From George Cook 1885-1888 (Box 1)
    - From Frank Cook 1880 (Box 1)
    - From Will S. Cook 1885-1890 (Box 1)
  - Teaching certificates 1887-1889 (Box 1)
- Vera Richardson
  Most of the letters in this collection are to Vera Richardson, the eldest daughter of Emma and Charles. Letters to Vera begin in 1901 and continue with increasing volume to 1918. After this they virtually end as she married Mr. Leigh S. Simpson with whom she had corresponded regularly since 1909. Other letters that she received are from her mother and other friends. The letters exemplify the life of a college girl in the 19 teens. Unfortunately this collection will not tell you anything about Owosso because most of the letters are from people in other places to the folks back home. Nor does it tell anything about Vera as a musician after her school days.
  - Letters to
    - 1901-1902 (Box 1)
    - 1903 (Box 1)
    - 1904 (Box 1)
    - 1905-1906 (Box 1)
    - 1907 (Box 1)
    - 1908 (Box 1)
    - 1909 (Box 1)
    - January-September 1910 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1910 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1911 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1911 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1912 (Box 1)
    - July-August 1912 (Box 1)
    - September-October 1912 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1912 (Box 1)
    - January-February 1913 (Box 1)
    - March-April 1913 (Box 1)
    - May-July 1913 (Box 1)
    - August-October 1913 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1913 (Box 1)
    - January-February 1914 (Box 1)
    - March-May 1914 (Box 1)
    - June-October 1914 (Box 1)
    - November-December 1914 (Box 1)
    - January 1, 1915-January 15, 1915 (Box 2)
    - January 16, 1915-January 31, 1915 (Box 2)
    - February 1, 1915-February 15, 1915 (Box 2)
    - February 16, 1915-February 28, 1915 (Box 2)
    - March 1915 (Box 2)
    - April-June 1915 (Box 2)
    - July-September 1915 (Box 2)
    - October-December 1916 (Box 2)
    - January-June 1917 (Box 2)
    - July-December 1917 (Box 2)
    - January-May 1918 (Box 2)
    - June-July 1918 (Box 2)
    - August 1918-1939 (Box 2)
  - Letters sent by
    - 1909-1915 (Box 2)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 2)
    - 1917-1927 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Letters to Otie Cook Jennings 1881-1888 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Don Richardson 1909-1917 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Max Richardson 1927-1943 (Box 2)
  - Letters, Max Richardson to... 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Letters to Evelyn Jetoria White (Richardson) 1938, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook of Don Richardson 1916-1919 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Business ledgers of Max Richardson 1953-1966, 5 volumes (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Family and institutions, 2 envelopes (Box 2)
  - Society of Sycamore Grove picnic March 21, 1926 (Folder UAl)
  - Tintypes (Folder UAx)